A Finding Aid to the Guy Pène Du Bois Papers in the Archives of American Art AAA.duboguyp
Archives of American Art
Guy Pène Du Bois papers
bulk 1920-1963
circa 1900-1963
AAA.duboguyp
Archives of American Art
1.8 Linear feet
The papers of painter and art critic Guy Pène Du Bois measure 1.8 linear feet and date from circa 1900 to 1963 with the bulk of the materials dating from 1920 to 1963. Found within the papers are biographical material; personal and professional correspondence, including letters from Royal Cortissoz and Edward Hopper; writings, including essays, short stories, and drafts of the autobiography Artists Say the Silliest Things; personal business records; printed material; and artwork.
Du Bois, Guy Pène, 1884-1958
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The Guy Pène Du Bois papers were donated by Du Bois' daughter, Yvonne McKenney, in 1971.
Separated Materials note
Sketches and etching proofs were loaned in 1970 for microfilming on reel 29 and returned to Du Bois' children Yvonne McKenney and William Pène Du Bois. In 1980 two diaries dating from 1913 to 1955, were loaned for microfilming on reel 2008 by Du Bois' daughter-in-law Willa Kim. Loaned material is available at Archives of American Art offices and for interlibrary loan but is not described in the container listing of this finding aid.
Related Archival Materials note
The Archives also holds the Guy Pène Du Bois and Mary Lightfoot Tarleton correspondence.
Existence and Location of Copies note
Portions of this collection are available on 35 mm microfilm reel 28 at the Archives of American Art offices, and through interlibrary loan. Researchers should note that the arrangement of the papers as described in this finding aid does not reflect the order of the collection on microfilm due to reprocessing.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical/Historical note
Painter and art critic Guy Pène Du Bois (1884-1958) lived and worked in New York City, New York and was known for his realist paintings, essays, and art reviews.
Du Bois was born in Brooklyn, New York to the art critic Henri Du Bois and his wife Laura. After he showed an early interest in art, his' family supported his decision to enroll in William Merritt Chase's New York School of Art at the age of 15. There, Du Bois trained with the realist painters Robert Henri and Kenneth Hayes Miller along with fellow students George Bellows, Edward Hopper, and Rockwell Kent. In 1905, he traveled to Paris and studied briefly with the artist Thèophile Steinlen, but returned to New York the following year after the death of his father. To help support his family, he found work as an illustrator and cartoonist for the New York American, and was promoted to the position of art critic for the newspaper in 1909.
In 1911, Du Bois married his wife, Florence Duncan, and became an assistant writer for the New York Tribune under Royal Cortissoz (1913). Du Bois also wrote art reviews for the New York Post (1916-1918), and was a writer and later editor of Arts and Decoration (1913-1915, 1917-1921). During these years, Du Bois also began to establish a career as a realist painter of note. His work was included in the 1913 Armory Show, after which he signed on as a member of the Kraushaar Gallery stable. Throughout the 1910s, Du Bois exhibited in numerous galleries and museums, and held his first one-man show in 1918 at the Whitney Studio Club.
From 1920 to 1924, Du Bois taught at the Art Students League, and spent the latter part of the 1920s in France with his family. After seven years, he moved his family back to Connecticut and opened the Guy Pène Du Bois School of Art in Stonington, Connecticut. Throughout the 1930s, Du Bois continued painting and received commissions to design federal murals in upstate New York (1937) and Boston (1942). In 1940, Du Bois published his autobiography, Artists Say the Silliest Things. After the death of his wife in 1950, Du Bois lived and traveled with his daughter's family and died in her home in Boston in 1958.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of painter and art critic Guy Pène Du Bois measure 1.8 linear feet and date from circa 1900 to 1963 with the bulk of the materials dating from 1920 to 1963. Found within the papers are biographical material; personal and professional correspondence, including letters from Royal Cortissoz and Edward Hopper; writings, including essays, short stories, and drafts of the autobiography Artists Say the Silliest Things; personal business records; printed material; and artwork.
Biographical materials consist of certificates, a curriculum vitae, passport, and a photograph of two unidentified women.
Correspondence is primarily with Du Bois' family, friends, and business associates. The series includes significant correspondence from fellow art critic Royal Cortissoz; artists Raphael Soyer and Edward Hopper; and writers Samuel Duff McCoy, Lincoln Isham, and Newton Booth Tarkington. Other correspondents of note include C.W. Kraushaar Art Galleries and Du Bois' son, the children's book illustrator William Pène Du Bois.
Writings include book drafts of Du Bois' autobiography, Artists Say the Silliest Things, journal entries, 35 essays, 8 short stories, and various writing fragments and notes.
Personal business records consist of account and sales records from C.W. Kraushaar Art Galleries, book and publishing contracts, and receipts for art supply purchases.
Printed material includes a brochure for the Guy Pène Du Bois School of Art, clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs, and miscellaneous printed material.
Artwork consists of pen and ink sketches by Du Bois and a print by an unknown artist.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 6 series.
Biographical material, 1929-1954 (4 folders; Box 1)
Correspondence, 1908-1958 (0.5 linear feet; Box 1)
Writings, circa 1900-1954 (1.1 linear feet; Box 1-3)
Personal business records, circa 1920-1949 (3 folders; Box 3)
Printed material, circa 1920-1963 (0.3 linear feet; Box 3)
Artwork, circa 1920-1954 (2 folders; Box 3)
C.W. Kraushaar Art Galleries.; Cortissoz, Royal, 1869-1948; Hopper, Edward, 1882-1967; McCoy, Samuel Duff, 1882-; Pène du Bois, William, 1916-1993; Soyer, Raphael, 1899-1987; Tarkington, Booth, 1869-1946; Art critics--New York (State)--New York; Painters--New York (State)--New York; Painting, American--New York (State)--New York; Photographs; Prints; Sketches
- Biographical Material, 1929-1954; Series 1; 4 Folders Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  Biographical materials consist of certificates, a curriculum vitae, passport, and a photograph of two unidentified women.
  Arrangement note
  Materials are arranged by document type.
  - Certificates, 1940-1942 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Curriculum Vitae, circa 1935-1954 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Passport, 1929-1930 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Photograph, Two Unidentified Women, circa 1940-1954 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1908-1958; Series 2; 0.5 Linear feet Box 1
  Correspondence is primarily with Du Bois' family, friends, and business associates. The series includes significant correspondence from fellow art critic Royal Cortissoz; artists Raphael Soyer and Edward Hopper; and writers Samuel Duff McCoy, Lincoln Isham, and Newton Booth Tarkington. The over 180 letters to Lincoln Isham detail Du Bois' daily life, in addition to covering his thoughts on writing, philosophy, politics, and news of his family.
  Other correspondents of note include C.W. Kraushaar Art Galleries and Du Bois' son, the children's book illustrator William Pène Du Bois. There are also letters of condolences addressed to Du Bois' daughter, Yvonne McKenney.
  Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  - A Miscellaneous, 1940-1949 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - American Artists Group Inc., 1939-1954 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - B Miscellaneous, 1929-1952 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bartlett, Clay, 1949-1950 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - C Miscellaneous, 1936-1945 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Carnegie Institute, 1937-1949 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Cooper Union, 1942-1954 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Cortissoz, Royal, 1930-1933 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - C.W. Kraushaar Art Galleries, 1940-1947 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - D Miscellaneous, 1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Du Bois, George, 1951-1956 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Du Bois, Guy Pène, 1941-1954 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Du Bois, William Pène, 1944-1949 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Du Bois, William Pène and Jane, 1950-1953 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Du Bois, William Pène and Willa, 1953-1956 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Duncan, Rita Jean, 1950-1954 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Duncan, Robert, 1949-1955 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - E-H Miscellaneous, 1939-1954 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Hopper, Edward, 1931-1954 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - I Miscellaneous, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Isham, Lincoln and Lea, 1942-1955 (Box 1, Folder 25-27)
  - J-M Miscellaneous, 1908-1954 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Macy, George, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - McCoy, Samuel Duff and Neely, 1949-1953 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Merritt, Nancy Lucas, 1951-1954 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - N-P Miscellaneous, 1939-1954 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Q-S Miscellaneous, 1939-1952 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Soyer, Raphael, 1951-1955 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - T Miscellaneous, 1930-1940 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Tarkington, Newton Booth, 1943-1946 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - U Miscellaneous, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - U.S. Treasury Department, 1936-1938 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - V-W Miscellaneous, 1940-1950 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Watson, Forbes, 1932-1953 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - X-Z Miscellaneous, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Unknown and Illegible, circa 1940-1954 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Condolences, A-Z, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 43-44)
- Writings, circa 1900-1954; Series 3; 1.1 Linear feet Box 1-3
  Writings include book drafts of Du Bois' autobiography, Artists Say the Silliest Things, journal entries, 35 essays on various art related topics, 8 short stories, and various writing fragments and notes. The journal entries are primarily writing exercises in essay style and cover diverse topics of fashion, character studies, art history, and current events.
  - Book, Artists Say the Silliest Things, Part One, circa 1930-1940 (Box 1, Folder 45-46)
  - Book, Artists Say the Silliest Things, Part One (copy 1, incomplete), circa 1930-1940 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Book, Artists Say the Silliest Things, Part One (fragments), circa 1930-1940 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Book, Artists Say the Silliest Things, Part One (handwritten draft, incomplete), circa 1930-1940 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Book, Artists Say the Silliest Things, Part Two, circa 1930-1940 (Box 1, Folder 50-51)
  - Book, Artists Say the Silliest Things, Part Two (copy 1), circa 1930-1940 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Book, Artists Say the Silliest Things, Part Two (copy 2, incomplete), circa 1930-1940 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Book, Artists Say the Silliest Things, Part Two (handwritten draft), circa 1930-1940 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Book, Untitled, Chapters 1-2, circa 1920-1954 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Book Proposals, circa 1940-1954 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Book Reviews, circa 1920-1954 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Essay, "Apes and Angels in Art", circa 1930-1954 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Essay, "Art and Decoration", circa 1930-1954 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Essay, "Art and the Decline of the Bourgeoise", circa 1930-1954 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Essay, "Art is Art and Life is Life", circa 1930-1954 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Essay, "Children's Books", circa 1930-1954 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Essay, "Classicism", circa 1930-1954 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Essay, "Clothes and War and Art", circa 1930-1954 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Essay, "Contrasts and Contemporaneous Art", circa 1930-1954 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Essay, "Decoration", circa 1930-1954 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Essay, "Eclectics", circa 1930-1954 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Essay, "Disordered Notes of an Ex Art Critic", circa 1930-1954 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Essay, "Essay Written for an American", circa 1930-1954 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Essay, "Eyes are Windows", circa 1930-1954 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Essay, "Forbears of the Fashionable Linguists", circa 1930-1954 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Essay, "High Art and Hillbillies", circa 1930-1954 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Essay, "Holley and the Square", circa 1930-1954 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Essay, "Note on Fashion", circa 1930-1954 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Essay, "Note on Modern Art", circa 1930-1954 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Essay, "Note on Statues", circa 1930-1954 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Essay, "Note on the American Scene Painting", circa 1930-1954 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Essay, "On the Satirist", circa 1930-1954 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Essay, On Artists and World Affairs, circa 1930-1954 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Essay, On Children's Book Fair, circa 1930-1954 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Essay, On Denys Wortman, circa 1930-1954 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Essay, On French Modernism, circa 1930-1954 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Essay, On Intellectualism, circa 1930-1954 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Essay, On Seeing Art, circa 1930-1954 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Essay, On Space, circa 1930-1954 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Essay, On Style and Fashion, circa 1930-1954 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Essay, "Realism", circa 1930-1954 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Essay, "Romanticism", circa 1930-1954 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Essay, "Seeing Could Be Believing", circa 1930-1954 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Essay, "Seeing in Its Relation to the Visual Arts", circa 1930-1954 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Essay, "Turnabout in Art", circa 1930-1954 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Essay, "War and Art", circa 1930-1954 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Journal Entries, 1949-1953 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Stories, "1907 New York," "Question of Bravery," "Sailors," "The Square", circa 1930-1954 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Story, "Final Flourish", circa 1930-1954 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Story, "Over-Lord", circa 1930-1954 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Story, "Staten Island", circa 1920-1954 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Story, "Wild Horses in Harlem", circa 1930-1954 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Fragments, Handwritten, circa 1920-1954 (Box 2, Folder 31-32)
  - Fragments, Typescripts, circa 1920-1954 (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
  - Fragments, Introductions, circa 1920-1954 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Fragments, Stories, circa 1920-1954 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Notes, circa 1920-1954 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - "Letters of Frederick von Elder," by Unknown Author, circa 1920-1954 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - "Moral Freedom--Natural Law," by W.W. Sherman, circa 1920-1954 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Personal Business Records, circa 1920-1949; Series 4; 3 Folders Box 3
  Personal business records consist of account and sales records from C.W. Kraushaar Art Galleries, two book and publishing contracts, and miscellaneous receipts for art supply purchases.
  - Account Records, C.W. Kraushaar Art Galleries, 1937-1944 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Contracts, 1930-1945 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Receipts, circa 1920-1949 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Printed Material, circa 1920-1963; Series 5; 0.3 Linear feet Box 3
  Printed material includes a brochure for the Guy Pène Du Bois School of Art, clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs, and miscellaneous printed material.
  - Brochure, Guy Pène Du Bois School of Art, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Clippings, circa 1920-1963 (Box 3, Folder 12-13)
  - Clippings, 1920-1963 (Box 3, Folder 14-18)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1954-1960 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, Other Artists, 1942-1943 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Periodical, Magazine of Art, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, 1931-1945 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Artwork, circa 1920-1954; Series 6; 2 Folders Box 3
  Artwork consists of pen and ink sketches by Du Bois and a print by an unknown artist.
  Materials are arranged by artist.
  - Sketches, circa 1920-1954 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Artwork by Others, 1931 (Box 3, Folder 24)